Chapter 78.
Sistern and buckets.
Nimble as a cat, Tashego mounts a loft, and without altering his erect posture,
runs straight out upon the overhanging manard arm to the part where it exactly
projects over the hoisted ton. He has carried with him a light tackle called a
whip, consisting of only two parts, traveling through a single sheaved
block. Securing this block so that it hangs down from the yard arm, he swings
one end of the rope till it is caught and firmly held by a hand on deck. Then,
hand over hand down the other part, the Indian drops through the air, till
dextrously he lands on the summit of the head. There, still high elevated above
the rest of the company, to whom he vivaceiously cries, he seems some
Turkish muees, calling the good people to prayers from the top of a tower. A
short-handled sharp spade being sent up to him, he diligently searches for the
proper place to begin breaking into the ton. In this business he proceeds very
heedfully like a treasure hunter in some old house sounding the walls to find
where the gold is masoned in. By the time this cautious search is over, a
stout ironbound bucket precisely like a well bucket has been attached to one end
of the whip, while the other end being stretched across the deck is there held
by two or three alert hands. These last now hoist the bucket within grasp of the
Indian to whom another person has reached up a very long pole. Inserting
this pole into the bucket, Tash Teego downward guides the bucket into the ton
till it entirely disappears. Then giving the word to the seaman at the whip. Up
comes the bucket again, all bubbling like a dairy maid's pale of new milk.
Carefully lowered from its height, the full freighted vessel is caught by an
appointed hand and quickly emptied into a large tub. Then, remounting a loft, it
again goes through the same round until the deep sistern will yield no more.
Towards the end, Tashego has to ram his long pole harder and harder and deeper
and deeper into the ton until some 20 ft of the pole have gone down.
Now the people of the Peekquad had been bailing some time in this way. Several
tubs had been filled with the fragrant sperm when all at once a queer accident
happened. Whether it was that Tashego, that wild Indian, was so heedless and
reckless as to let go for a moment his one-handed hold on the great cabled
tackle suspending the head, or whether the place where he stood was so
treacherous and oozy, or whether the evil one himself would have it fall out
so, without stating his particular reasons. How it was exactly, there is no
telling now. But on a sudden, as the 80th or 90th bucket came suckingly up,
my God, poor Tashego, like the twin reciprocating bucket in a veritable
well, dropped head foremost down into this great ton of H Highleberg, and with
a horrible oily gurgling, went clean out of sight.
"Man overboard!" cried Dagu, who amid the general consternation, first came to
his senses. Swing the bucket this way.
And putting one foot into it so as the better to secure his slippery handhold
on the whip itself, the hoyers ran him high to the top of the head, almost
before Tashego could have reached its interior bottom. Meantime, there was a
terrible tumult. Looking over the side, they saw the before lifeless head
throbbing and heaving just below the surface of the sea, as if that moment
seized with some momentous idea, whereas it was only the poor Indian
unconsciously revealing by those struggles the perilous depth to which he had sunk.
At this instant, while Dagu on the summit of the head was clearing the
whip, which had somehow got foul of the great cutting tackles, a sharp cracking
noise was heard, and to the unspeakable horror of all, one of the two enormous
hooks suspending the head tore out, and with a vast vibration, the enormous mass
sideways swung, till the drunk ship reeled and shook as if smitten by an
iceberg. The one remaining hook upon which the entire strain now depended
seemed every instant to be on the point of giving way, an event still more
likely from the violent motions of the head. "Come down! Come down!" yelled the
seaman to Dagu. But with one hand holding on to the heavy tackles so that
if the head should drop, he would still remain suspended, the negro, having
cleared the foul line, rammed down the bucket into the now collapsed well,
meaning that the buried harpooner should grasp it and so be hoisted out.
In heaven's name, man, cried Stub. Are you ramming home a cartridge there? I've
help him jamming that ironbound bucket on top of his head. I've asked, "Will
you stand clear of the tackle?" cried a voice like the bursting of a rocket.
Almost in the same instant, with a thunderboom, the enormous mass dropped
into the sea like Niagara's table rock into the whirlpool. The suddenly
relieved hull rolled away from it to far down her glittering copper, and all
caught their breath as half swinging now over the sailor's heads and now over the
water. Dagu through a thick mist of spray was dimly beheld clinging to the
pendulus tackles while poor buried alive Tachego was sinking utterly down to the
bottom of the sea. But hardly had the blinding vapor cleared away when a naked
figure with a boarding sword in his hand was for one swift moment seen hovering
over the bullwarks. The next a loud splash announced that my brave Quiquake
had dived to the rescue. One packed rush was made to the side, and every eye
counted every ripple, as moment followed moment, and no sign of either the sinker
or the diver could be seen. Some hands now jumped into a boat alongside and
pushed a little off from the ship.
"Haha!" Ah! cried Dagu all at once from his now quiet swinging perch overhead,
and looking further off from the side, we saw an arm thrust upright from the
blue waves. A strange sight to see, as an arm thrust forth from the grass over
a grave. "Both, both. It is both," cried Dagu again with a joyful shout, and soon
after Quiqu was seen boldly striking out with one hand, and with the other,
clutching the long hair of the Indian.
Drawn into the waiting boat, they were quickly brought to the deck, but Tashega
was long in coming too, and Quiquake did not look very brisk.
Now, how had this noble rescue been accomplished? Why diving after the
slowly descending head, Quiquake, with his keen sword, had made side lunges
near its bottom, so as to scuttle a large hole there, then dropping his
sword, had thrust his long arm far inwards and upwards, and so hauled out
poor Tash by the head. He avered that upon first thrusting in for him a leg
was presented, but well knowing that that was not as it ought to be, and
might occasion great trouble, he had thrust back the leg, and by a dextrous
heave and toss, had wrought a Somerset upon the Indian, so that with the next
trial he came forth in the good old way, head foremost. As for the great head
itself, that was doing as well as could be expected.
And thus through the courage and great skill in obstetrics of Quequ, the
deliverance, or rather delivery of Tashtego was successfully accomplished,
in the teeth too of the most untoward and apparently hopeless impediments,
which is a lesson by no means to be forgotten. Midwiffery should be taught
in the same course with fencing and boxing, riding and rowing. I know that
this queer adventure of the gay headers will be sure to seem incredible to some
landsmen, though they themselves have either seen or heard of someone's
falling into a sistern ashore. An accident which not seldom happens, and
with much less reason, too, than the Indians, considering the exceeding
slipperiness of the curb of the sperm whales well. But per adventure, it may
be sagaciously urged, "How is this? We thought the tissued infiltrated head of
the sperm whale was the lightest and most quirky part about him, and yet thou
makes it sink in an element of far greater specific gravity than itself. We
have thee there. Not at all, but I have ye. For at the time poor Tash fell in,
the case had been nearly emptied of its lighter contents, leaving little but the
dense tenderness wall of the well, a double welded, hammered substance, as I
have before said, much heavier than the seawater, and a lump of which sinks in
it like lead almost. But the tendency to rapid sinking in this substance was in
the present instance materially counteracted by the other parts of the
head remaining undetached from it, so that it sank very slowly and
deliberately indeed, affording Quiquake a fair chance for performing his agile
obsetrics on the run, as you may say.
Yes, it was a running delivery. So it was.
Now had Tashego perished in that head, it had been a very precious perishing,
smothered in the very whitest and daintiest of fragrance burmicetti,
coffened, hursed, and tombmed in the secret inner chamber and sanctum
sanctorum of the whale. Only one sweeter end can readily be recalled. The
delicious death of an Ohio honey hunter, who seeking honey in the crotch of a
hollow tree, found such an exceeding store of it that leaning too far over,
it sucked him in, so that he died imbalmed. How many think ye have
likewise fallen into Plato's honey head, and sweetly perished there?